## Curriculum Vitae / Résumé



# Gary Collins

LinkedIn: garypcollins

gary.p.collins@gmail.com

Skype: garycollinswork@outlook.com

View this online



https://goo.gl/8xKE0w

# Web Engineer

Summary

I'm a Front End developer with 5+ years of web dev experience and 10+ years of commercial and enterprise development experience. I pride myself on producing quality code using TDD with Red/Green/Refactor and Agile methodologies.

I have a passion for all things UX and Design and I believe that all software should be simple and reliable enough for my Mother to use it, while flexible and powerful enough to enable power users to do more and create more.

Working on web apps with millions of users, I understand the need for scalable, efficient and performant code and understand that usability and accessibility for every single one of those users is very important.

My core skill-set includes HTML5 and CSS3/SASS, ES6 JavaScript and TypeScript, with exposure to MVC frameworks like Knockout and React and other associated technologies such as NodeJS, npm, Grunt, Mocha, Jasmine, Browserify and Git.

## Job Experience

# September 2013 - Present Skype / Microsoft

#### Software Engineer II

Front End developer on the Skype for Web client, both at http://web.skype.com and in the Outlook and Office365 Skype integrations.

- I first worked on the first generation Skype integration for Outlook online and Bing.com, a simple IM and calling App.
- Then produced the first version of the SWX (Skype Web eXperience) Bootstrapper, which loaded the Skype for Web package via an external configuration service. This enabled us to move to a continuous deployment system, allowing us to release with a weekly cadence.
- Once the Skype for Web client was conceived, I produced and designed some of the first code in the model layer, before being a key contributor to the UI, model and service
- Now Skype for Web has hundreds of millions of monthly connected users on platforms including Windows, Mac and Linux.

#### Recent highlights:

- Lead the development effort to add CaaP (Conversation as a Platform aka Bots) support to Skype for Web, creating the Bot discovery, buddying experiences and the model layer support for having Bot contacts.
- One of the main contributors when we added PSTN (calling to landlines and mobiles) to Skype for Web.
- Added the Contact profile view and the ability to Block, Unblock and Delete contacts.
- Brought Skype for Web up to the Microsoft Accessibility B spec.
- Lead the client-side effort to transition to the new Skype Contacts services.
- Contributed to the Skype for Web modularization effort in order to enable the model layer to be used as a customized and lightweight SDK internally and, one day, open sourced for partners.

 Began work to redesign the Bot discovery experience into something more akin to an App store

## July 2012 - September 2013

### InMobi Ltd

#### Senior Engineer - App Publish

- Lead UI development for the InMobi App Publish product
- Composite JavaScript application
- Built using MVC principles with Backbone.js and Marionette.js with jQuery and custom jQuery UI widgets
- HTML5 + CCS3 templates using Underscore.js and JSPs
- Java based RESTful web services back end, hosted on Apache Tomcat
- AJAX requests using JSON over HTTP

## August 2007 – July 2012 Metaflow Solutions Ltd

#### Senior Engineer

- Lead the design and HTML/CCS and JavaScript development on the Metaflow Ark and MetaServer products with Java Servlet and JSP development
- Java development of the Metaflow desktop client application, with Eclipse RCP, SWT and OSGi
- XML based transport layer communication (WBXML)
- Java web services

## February 2007 – August 2007

Infospace

#### Core Developer

- Development on the Infospace Mobile Application framework
- Maintained APIs for J2ME and MIDP applications
- Development of the Infospace b2b website
- Worked with Apache HTTP Server and Apache Tomcat servlet container as well as MySQL Database server running on both Linux and Microsoft Windows Server 2003 RC2 servers
- Java web services

## October 2005 - February 2007

iomo

#### Porting Programmer

- Took 'finished' builds of J2ME games and made them work on actual handsets
- Fixing the bugs, resizing and optimising the code and assets for the multitude of different screen sizes and capabilities of all the Java-capable mobile handsets from manufacturers such as Nokia, SonyEricsson, Motorola, HTC and LG

### Education

### 2002 - 2005

## University of Southampton

BSc Computer Science - Second class honours, upper division (2:1)

### References

# Damjan Došen

Current: Principal Software Engineering Manager for Skype Consumer at Microsoft

damjan.dosen@microsoft.com LinkedIn: damjandosen dosendamjan@gmail.com

+44 (0)7920 700 695

### Abdellah Elamiri

Current: Senior Software Engineering Manager for Skype Consumer at Microsoft

abdellah.elamiri@microsoft.com

abdellah. elamiri@outlook.com

+44 (0)7530 579 452

LinkedIn: elamiri

# Paul Chapman

Current: Senior Technical Lead at INQ Mobile
Previous: Director at Metaflow Solutions Ltd and Senior Technical Lead at InMobi

paul@inqmobile.com +44 (0)7900 167 706 LinkedIn: paul-chapman-953b428

# Matthew Cope

Current: Director at Software AG
Previous: Senior Programmer at Infospace and IOMO

matthew.cope@metismo.com LinkedIn: matthew-cope-5418a01

### Nick Reed

Current: Director Research & Development at Software AG
Previous: Technical Manager - Games at Infospace & Technical Director at IOMO

nick.reed@softwareag.com LinkedIn: ncikr

# Interests

- Science and new technology
- Bleeding edge web technologies
- Design UX, Graphic and Architecture
- Photography
- Music and DJing
- XBOX Gaming
- Sports Skiing/Snowboarding, Football, American Football, Table Tennis, Pool, Cricket, Badminton